  <sect1 id="Acknowledgments">
    <title>Acknowledgments</title>
    
    <para>
      The first version of this guide was written by Rob Savoye.  If not for
      his tireless efforts, this book - and this project - would never have
      come this far. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      John Steinhart has also been supportive of the project from the
      beginning. I have shamelessly plagiarized one of his early
      announcement emails in the early part of this chapter. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Ann Barcomb was instrumental in taking this guide from the 0.3.0 to
      the 0.4.0 version, incorporating the many changes that came with &app;
      version 0.8.0. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
      &app; is based on the public domain program
      <application>GameSWF</application>, a graphics library
      for games that contains the heart of a SWF interpreter.  In December
      2005, &app; was forked from <application>GameSWF</application> and
      repackaged in the GNU project style, and a major recoding started.
    </para>

    <para>
      &app; makes use of jemalloc, which is copyrighted by Jason Evans
      &lt;jasone@FreeBSD.org&gt;.  The terms of the license follow:
    </para>

<para>
  Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
  modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
  are met:
  1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
     notice(s), this list of conditions and the following disclaimer as
     the first lines of this file unmodified other than the possible
     addition of one or more copyright notices.
  2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
     notice(s), this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in
     the documentation and/or other materials provided with the
     distribution.
    </para>
 
    <para>
  THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER(S) ``AS IS'' AND ANY
  EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
  IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
  PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDER(S) BE
  LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
  CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF
  SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR
  BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY,
  WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE
  OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE,
  EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
    </para>
  
    <para>
      Finally, thanks to all of the &app; developers I haven't mentioned for
      all their hard work, and for answering my unending questions. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
