<chapter id="bugreport">
  <title>Reporting Bugs</title>

<para>
The &app; project relies on the community to use and test the player; feedback is critical to any successful project.  Not only does it let us know that people use &app;, but it helps us understand the community's needs.  &app; uses a bug tracker on <ulink url="http://savannah.gnu.org" /> to manage these reports.
</para>

  <para>
When filing a report, please follow the guidelines below. The better your bug report is, the easier it will be for the
    developers to address the issue.
</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_newcheckout">Compile the latest
        &app; build.</link>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_search">Determine if the bug was
        previously reported.</link>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_guidelines">Review the bug writing 
        guidelines.</link>
      </para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>


  <sect1 id="bugstep_newcheckout">
    <title>Compile the latest &app; build</title>
    <para>
      Obtain a copy of the latest <link linkend="sourcerepo">development
      checkout</link> or <link linkend="sourcesnapshot">development
      snapshot</link>.  Put the source in an empty directory, then
      <link linkend="pre-configuration">configure</link> and 
      <link linkend="compile">compile</link> &app;.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you are able to replicate the bug in the latest version, 
      <link linkend="bugstep_search">proceed to the next step</link>.  If you cannot replicate the bug with the newer version, the problem may have been solved, or the issue may involve your environment
    </para>

    <para>
To check this, create a fresh build of the version in which you encountered the bug.  If you can reproduce the bug with the fresh copy of the original version, but cannot with the latest version, this is most likely a resolved bug.
</para>

<para>
If you cannot reproduce the bug, it may still be unclear whether the bug is related to your environment or a &app; bug.  Try to determine the source of the problem.  &app; offers several helpful debugging options in the configure stage, and many verbosity options at the command line to help.
</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_search">
    <title>Determine if the bug was previously reported</title>
    <para>
      Search the <ulink type="https"
      url="https://savannah.gnu.org/bugs/?group=gnash">&app;
      bug tracker</ulink> to see if the bug has already been identified.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the issue has already been reported, you should not file
      a bug report.  However, you may add some additional information
      to the ticket if you feel that it will be beneficial to the
      developers.  For instance, if someone reported a memory issue
      on Ubuntu GNU/Linux, and you noticed the same problem on OpenBSD,
      your stacktrace would be useful.  Conversely, adding a "me too"
      note to a feature request is not helpful.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_guidelines">
    <title>Review the bug writing guidelines</title>
    <para>
      A good bug report should be precise, explicit, and discrete.
      This means that there should be just one bug per ticket, and
      that a ticket should contain the following information:
</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem>
<para>
          An overview of the problem;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          Instructions on how to replicate the bug;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          A description of what happened when you performed the steps
          to replicate the bug, and what you expected to happen;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          Your system information: operating system name and version, as
          well as the versions of major <link 
          linkend="codedepend">dependencies</link>;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          The release number or checkout timestamp for the version of &app;
          where you observe the problem;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          The file <filename>config.log</filename>, which should be
          attached as a file; and
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          A descriptive title.
</para>
        </listitem> 
      </itemizedlist>
<para>
      Include any additional information that you feel might be useful
      to the developers.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_file">
    <title>Filing a bug report</title>
    <para>
      After following the steps described above, you can file a bug report at 
      <ulink type="https"
      url="https://savannah.gnu.org/bugs/?group=gnash" />.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
    
