<chapter id="bugreport">
  <title>Reporting Bugs</title>

  <para>
    The better your bug report is, the easier it will be for the
    developers to address the issue.
    Please follow the three steps described below before filing a bug
    report:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_newcheckout">Compile the latest
        &app; build.</link>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_search">Determine if the bug was
        previously reported.</link>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <link linkend="bugstep_guidelines">Review the bug writing 
        guidelines.</link>
      </para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_newcheckout">
    <title>Compile the latest &app; build</title>
    <para>
      Obtain a copy of the latest <link linkend="sourcerepo">development
      checkout</link> or <link linkend="sourcesnapshot">development
      snapshot</link>.  Put the source in an empty directory, then
      <link linkend="pre-configuration">configure</link> and 
      <link linkend="compile">compile</link> &app;.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are able to replicate the bug, 
      <link linkend="bugstep_search">proceed to the next step</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the bug does not persist, the problem may have been solved, or
      the issue may involve your environment.  By creating a fresh build
      of your original version and trying to replicate the bug you
      can determine if it is an environmental issue or a resolved bug.
      If you are able to replicate the bug, the problem has been fixed
      and there is no need to file a bug report.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the bug is no longer visible, the problem may be related to
      your environment.  Try to determine the source of the conflict
      so that you can include this information in your bug report.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_search">
    <title>Determine if the bug was previously reported</title>
    <para>
      Search the <ulink type="https"
      url="https://savannah.gnu.org/bugs/?group=gnash">&app;
      bug tracker</ulink> to see if the bug has already been identified.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the issue has already been reported, you should not file
      a bug report.  However, you may add some additional information
      to the ticket if you feel that it will be beneficial to the
      developers.  For instance, if someone reported a memory issue
      on Ubuntu GNU/Linux, and you noticed the same problem on OpenBSD,
      your stacktrace would be useful.  Conversely, adding a "me too"
      note to a feature request is not helpful.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_guidelines">
    <title>Review the bug writing guidelines</title>
    <para>
      A good bug report should be precise, explicit, and discrete.
      This means that there should be just one bug per ticket, and
      that a ticket should contain the following information:
</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
        <listitem>
<para>
          An overview of the problem;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          Instructions on how to replicate the bug;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          A description of what happened when you performed the steps
          to replicate the bug, and what you expected to happen;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          Your system information: operating system name and version, as
          well as the versions of major <link 
          linkend="codedepend">dependencies</link>;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          The release number or checkout timestamp for the version of &app;
          where you observe the problem;
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          The file <filename>config.log</filename>, which should be
          attached as a file; and
</para>
        </listitem> 
        <listitem>
<para>
          A descriptive title.
</para>
        </listitem> 
      </itemizedlist>
<para>
      Include any additional information that you feel might be useful
      to the developers.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="bugstep_file">
    <title>Filing a bug report</title>
    <para>
      After following the steps described above, you can
      <ulink type="https"
      url="https://savannah.gnu.org/bugs/?group=gnash">file a
      bug report</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
    
