<title>Features</title>

<para>
  Some switches can be used during configuration to enable or disable
  features of &app;. Some of the most important configuration options
  are:
</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
    <listitem>
    <para>
<option>--enable-gui</option> lets you specify your GUI of choice.
The default option is GTK.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
<option>--enable-renderer</option> allows a renderer to be
chosen.  The default renderer is OpenGL.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
<option>--enable-media</option> permits a media handler to be
selected.  The default is FFMPEG with SDL sound.
    </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<para>
  A complete list of available features follows.
</para>

<table id="tb-config-features">
<title>Configuration Options - Features</title>
<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec colname='Option' />
<colspec colname='Function' />
<thead>
<row>
  <entry>Option</entry>
  <entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-debugger</option></entry>
  <entry>Enable support for the Flash debugger. The debugger is
        mainly of interest to Flash developers.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-dmalloc</option></entry>
  <entry>Enable support for the DMalloc memory debugging tool.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry> <option>--enable-docbook</option></entry>
  <entry>  Enable the generation of HTML and PDF versions of the documentation
	from the XML. You will then be able to use <command>make html</command> and <command>make pdf</command>.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>  <option>--enable-embedded</option></entry>
  <entry> Link to Qt-embedded, do not use X. This is only used by
        Klash</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry> <option>--disable-fork</option></entry>
  <entry>Disable the plugin from forking the standalone player, and
        using a thread for the player instead. Currently forking
        the standalone player gives you the best results.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-ghelp</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable support for the GNOME help system.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--disable-glext</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Disable using GtkGlExt, which forces the use of SDL
        instead. By default if the GtkGL extension for Gtk is found
        by the configure script, the GTK-enabled GUI is built.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-gui=gtk|sdl|kde|fltk|fb</option></entry>
  <entry><para>Select the Graphic User Interface to use (choose one).</para>
 <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>GTK</term>
	  <listitem>
<para>
    The GTK+ toolkit, which is the default GUI.
    Said to interwork particularly well with firefox.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>SDL</term>
	  <listitem>
<para>
    Simple DirectMedia Layer, a simple and portable GUI.
    Its sound facilities are used when --enable-media=ffmpeg|mad
    regardless of whether it is also in charge of the GUI.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>KDE</term>
	  <listitem>
<para>
    An interface adapted to the KDE Desktop Environment.
    This must be selected when building the Konqueror plugin
    "klash". Furthermore, the only renderer that currently
    works with KDE is opengl.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>FLTK</term>
	  <listitem>
<para>
    Fast Light ToolKit, low on resource usage.
    Since all build using fltk are now broken, we declare it
    "for developers".
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>FB</term>
	  <listitem>
<para>
    The Linux Frame Buffer, also known as /dev/fb0.
    AGG is the only renderer that can currently be used
    with the framebuffer GUI.
</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-i810-lod-bias</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable fix for Intel 810 LOD bias problem. Older versions
        of libMesa on the Intel i810 or i815 graphics processor
        need this flag or Gnash will core dump. This has been
        fixed in newer versions (summer 2005) of libMesa.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--disable-klash</option></entry>
  <entry>Disable support for Konqueror plugin. If
        <option>--disable-plugin</option> is not specified
        and support for building KDE programs is found, Klash is
        built by default. This option limits the plugin to only
        the Mozilla/Firefox one.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-libsuffix</option>
</entry>
  <entry><filename>/lib</filename> directory suffix (64,32,none=default). This is only
        used by Klash.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-mac</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Link to Qt/Mac (don't use X). This is only used by
        Klash.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-media=ffmpeg|mad|gst</option>
</entry>
  <entry>  <para>
        Select the specified media decoder and sound engine.
        FFMPEG and MAD use the SDL sound engine; GST uses its own.
	MAD only decodes MP3 sounds and uses integer arithmetic while
	the others also decode video files and use floating point.
        <option>FFMPEG</option> is the default decoder.
      </para>
      <para>
        You should only select one media decoder.
      </para></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--disable-plugin</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable building the plugin. By default the
        Mozilla Firefox plugin is built if all the required
        files are found by configure. Specify the 
        <option>--with-plugindir=</option> option to specify where the
        plugin should be installed.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>    <option>--enable-qtopia</option>
</entry>
  <entry>  Link to Qt-embedded, link to the Qtopia
        Environment. This is only used by Klash.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-renderer=opengl|cairo|agg</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable support for the a graphics backend. Currently
        only <option>opengl</option> and
        <option>agg</option> work sufficiently. OpenGL is
        used when you have hardware accelerated graphics. AGG i
        used when you do not have hardware accelerated
        graphics. Typically most desktop machines have OpenGL
        support, and most embedded systems do not. OpenGl is the
        default when building Gnash, although the quality of AGG's
        rendering is currently superior to OpenGL.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-sdk-install</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable installing the libraries and headers as an SDK.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--disable-shared</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable installing the shared libraries and headers.
        Note that the extensions mechanism may not work if shared
        libraries are disabled.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-strict</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Turn verbose GCC compiler warnings. By default only
        <option>-Wall</option> is used with GCC.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-fps-debug</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Enable FPS debugging code. When this feature is compiled in you can use the -f switch of &app;
	to have FPS printed at regular intervals.</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-write</option></entry>
  <entry>Makes the Mozilla plugin write the currently playing SWF movie to <filename>/tmp</filename>.
</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry><option>--enable-mit-shm</option>
</entry>
  <entry>Add support for using the MIT-SHM X extensions when available. 
	Currently only available using GTK gui and AGG renderer, and known to be
	bogus in handling of expose events (http://savannah.gnu.org/bugs/?20301).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
