<sect1 id="configfeatures">
  <title>Features</title>
  
  <para>
    Some switches can be used during configuration to enable or disable
    features of &app;. Some of the most important configuration options
    are:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<option>--enable-gui</option> lets you specify your GUI of choice.
	The default option is GTK.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<option>--enable-renderer</option> allows a renderer to be
	chosen.  The default renderer is AGG.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<option>--enable-media</option> permits a media handler to be
	selected.  The default is Gstreamer. 
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    A complete list of available features follows.
  </para>
  
  <table id="tb-config-features">
    <title>Configuration Options - Features</title>
    <tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <thead>
	<row>
	  <entry>Option</entry>
	  <entry>Function</entry>
	</row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-debugger</option></entry>
	  <entry>Enable support for the Flash debugger. The debugger is
	  mainly of interest to Flash developers, and is still under development.</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-lirc</option></entry>
	  <entry>
	    Enable support for the LIRC remote control protocol.
	  </entry>
	</row>

	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-cygnal</option></entry>
	  <entry>
	    Build the Cygnal streaming media server.
	  </entry>
	</row>

	<row>
	  <entry><option>--disable-menus</option></entry>
	  <entry>
	    Disable building all the menus for the GUI. THis is used
	    by mobile devices without as much screen space.
	  </entry>
	</row>

	<row>
	  <entry> <option>--enable-docbook</option></entry>
	  <entry>  Enable the generation of HTML, INFO, and MAN
	  versions of the documentation from the Docbook XML. You will
	  then be able to use <command>make html</command>,
	  <command>make info</command>, and <command>make
	  man</command> commands. By default, man,info and html pages
	  are generated.</entry>
	</row>

	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-gui=gtk|sdl|kde|fltk|fb|hildon|alp</option></entry>
	  <entry><para>Select the Graphic User Interface to use (choose one).</para>
	  <variablelist>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>GTK</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The GTK+ toolkit, which is the default GUI.
		  Said to interwork particularly well with firefox.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>Hildon</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The Hildon toolkist is based on GTK+, and is use by
		  some mobile devices.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>ALP</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The ALP "Hiker" GUI is used for the Access Linux platform.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>SDL</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Simple DirectMedia Layer, a simple and portable GUI.
		  Its sound facilities are used when --enable-media=ffmpeg
		  regardless of whether it is also in charge of the GUI.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>KDE</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  An interface adapted to the KDE Desktop Environment.
		  This must be selected when building the Konqueror plugin
		  "klash". Furthermore, the only renderer that currently
		  works with KDE is opengl.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>FLTK</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Fast Light ToolKit, low on resource usage.
		  Since all builds using fltk are now broken, we declare it
		  "for developers".
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	    <varlistentry>
	      <term>FB</term>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The Linux Frame Buffer, also known as /dev/fb0.
		  AGG is the only renderer that can currently be used
		  with the framebuffer GUI.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </varlistentry>
	  </variablelist>
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-media=ffmpeg|gst|none</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>  <para>
	    Select the specified media decoder and sound engine.
	    FFmpeg uses the SDL sound engine; GST uses its own.
	    <option>GST</option> is the default decoder.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You should only select one media decoder.
	  </para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <option>--disable-nsapi</option>
	    <option>--enable-nsapi</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Force disable/enable building the NPAPI plugin.
	  By default the Mozilla plugin is built if the GTK gui 
	  is selected.  Specify the 
	  <option>--with-npapi-plugindir=</option> option to specify where the
	  plugin should be installed.
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <option>--disable-kparts</option>
	    <option>--enable-kparts</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Force disable/enable building the KPARTS plugin. By default the
	  KDE plugin is built if the kde gui is selected. 
	  Specify the <option>--with-kde-plugindir=</option> and
	  <option>--with-kde-servicesdir=</option> options (or more generally
	  the <option>--with-kde-pluginprefix=</option> one) to specify where the
	  plugin should be installed. The default installation dir is extracted
	  from kde-config.
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry>
	    <option>--disable-plugins</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Disable build of both kparts and npapi plugins</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-renderer=opengl|cairo|agg</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Enable support for a graphics backend. Currently
	  only <option>opengl</option> and
	  <option>agg</option> work sufficiently. Use OpenGL
	  when you have hardware accelerated graphics. Use AGG
	  when you do not have hardware accelerated
	  graphics or when you are building for a wide audience.
          Typically most desktop machines have OpenGL
	  support, and most embedded systems do not. AGG is the
	  default when building Gnash, although the speed of OpenGL's
	  rendering is currently superior to AGG.</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-sdk-install</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Enable installing the libraries and headers as an SDK.
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--disable-shared</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Enable installing the shared libraries and headers.
	  Note that the extensions mechanism may not work if shared
	  libraries are disabled.</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-strict</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Turn verbose GCC compiler warnings. By default only
	  <option>-Wall</option> is used with GCC.</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-fps-debug</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Enable FPS debugging code. When this feature is compiled in you can use the -f switch of &app;
	  to have FPS printed at regular intervals.</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--enable-write</option></entry>
	  <entry>Makes the Mozilla plugin write the currently playing SWF movie to <filename>/tmp</filename>.
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--disable-sa-launcher</option></entry>
	  <entry>Drops the NPAPI plugin support for writing a standalone executable launcher script for the currently playing SWF movie to <filename>/tmp</filename>. Note that you'll still need to add a 'writelauncher' string to your GNASH_OPTIONS environment variable for the script to be created, even if the compile-time support is enabled.
	  </entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><option>--disable-mit-shm</option>
	  </entry>
	  <entry>Disable support for the MIT-SHM X extensions.
	  Currently support is only available using GTK gui and AGG renderer.
	  Keeping it enabled is not a problem as it will not be used if not
	  available in the current X session.
	  </entry>
	</row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>
</sect1>
