<sect4 id="asnetconnection">
  <title>NetConnection ActionScript Class</title>

  <para>
    This class implements an NetConnection object. The NetConnection
    object opens a client connection to load an FLV video file from a
    local system, or a remote one using the RTMP or RTMPT protocols.
    RTMP connections use port 1935, and RTMPT connections use port 80.
  </para>

  <para>
    This class was first introduced for swf v7 and the behavior has
    recently changed slightly to allow the loading of files from
    external systems. Prior to this, you were required to pass NULL to
    this class. Gnash handles both cases. The older behavior is default
    when connecting to the local filesystem for the file.
  </para>

  <para>
    The URL that can be passed to <emphasis>connect()</emphasis> in newer
    versions of the swf format is as follows:
    <programlisting>
      protocol:[//host][:port]/appname/[instanceName]
    </programlisting>
    For protocol, specify either <emphasis>RTMP</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>RTMPT</emphasis>. If rtmp is specified, SWF Player will create
    a client connection. If <emphasis>RTMPT</emphasis> is specified, SWF
    Player will create an HTTP "tunneling" connection to the server.
  </para>

  <para>
    You can omit the host parameter if the SWF movie is served from
    localhost. If the instanceName parameter is omitted, SWF Player
    connects to the application's default instance (_definst_).
  </para>

    <sect5 id="netconnectionmethods">
	<title>The Methods of the  Class</title>

	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>the same host where Flash Communication Server is installed
	  <term>NetConnection.connect(const char *)</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Connect to a local or remote system to load a
	      FLV file. Arg can be NULL, or a URL.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
    </sect5>

<!--    
    <sect5 id="netconnectionprops">
      <title>The Properties of the NetConnection Class</title>
      
      <para>
	<variablelist>
	  
	</variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect5>
-->
    
    <sect5 id="netconnectionconf">
      <title>NetConnection Class Conformance</title>
      
      <informaltable frame="all">
	<?dbhtml table-width="75%" ?>
	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry valign="top">
		<para>Class Name</para>
	      </entry>
	      <entry valign="top">
		<para>Conformance</para>
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry valign="top" align="left">
		<para>NetConnection.connect()</para>
	      </entry>
	      <entry valign="top" align="center">
		<para>
		  This method is partially implemented. It can only be
		  used in conjunction with the <link
		  linkend="asnetstream">NetStream</link> and <link
		  linkend="asvideo">Video</link> classes; it cannot
		  load a FLV file by itself.
		</para>
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </informaltable>
  </sect5>  
</sect4>
